I am sorry, I had to speak in Marathi language
Omlouvám se, musela jsem mluvit v maráthí,
because I had to tell them something which I don't want you to know.
protože dnes jsem jim musela říct něco, o čem nechci, abyste věděli.
Today is a great day, I should say in a way,
Dnes je významný den,
because I am going to tell you one thing great.
protože dnes vám chci říct jednu významnou věc.
That is Shri Gyaneshwara - in Marathi they call it 'Dnyaneshwara' -
Gjanéšwara, v maráthi říkají Dňanéšwara,
He was the incarnation of Kartikeya.
byl inkarnací Kartikéji.
And Saraswati, who was a virgin, she looked after Him like Her own son.
Sarasvatí, která byla pannou, se o něj starala, jako by to byl její syn.
He was the brother of Shri Ganapati but She looked after Him.
Byl bratrem Šrí Ganapatiho, ale starala se o něj Ona.
And then also there’s description how He was born and all those (things),
Existuje popis jeho narození a podobně,
is very interesting.
je to velmi zajímavé.
But here in this place, in this Maharashtra, He took His incarnation.
Ale tady na tomto místě v Maháráštře, se inkarnoval.
And also there were many great, great, very great saints
Žilo tu mnoho a mnoho velkých světců,
in so many numbers took place, took their birth in this Maharashtra.
tolik světců, kteří se narodili právě v Maháráštře.
But such horrible people, they tortured their lives.
Byli tu ale tak hrozní lidé, že život světců býval utrpením.
Worse than Christian Inquisition I tell you;
Bylo to horší než křesťanská inkvizice,
worse than any inquisition anywhere.
horší než kterákoliv inkvizice.
Individually they attacked.
Lidé je napadali sami za sebe.
And that same people are born again
Tito lidé se nyní rodí znova
in this great country of Maharashtra.
v této skvělé zemi Maháráštry.
They are very talented people; they write very well.
Jsou to velmi talentovaní lidé, velice dobře píšou,
Their language is so rich.
jejich jazyk je tak bohatý.
You can see that, what description
Vidíte, jak je popis realizované duše,
of a realized soul, given by Gyaneshwara, is so beautiful.
který napsal Gjánéšvara, tak nádherný.
He says that, "The moon doesn’t run after moonlight,
Říká: „Měsíc neutíká za měsíčním svitem,
the sun doesn’t run after sunlight.
slunce neutíká za světlem slunce.
In that way a realized soul doesn’t bother about his own glory.
Realizovaná duše se nestará o svou vlastní slávu.
The sun shines till it shines, then it takes back all his rays.
Slunce svítí, dokud svítí, a pak si vezme zpět své paprsky.
Whatever work the rays have to do they do it. And the sun is just watching,
Paprsky odvedou všechnu práci,
watching all the work, then he takes them back.
Dívá se na celé dílo, a pak si je vezme zpět.
And he gets completely contained within himself”.
Je zcela pohroužen do ticha svého nitra.“
Samavun ghene, completely contained within himself.
„Samavun ghene“, zcela pohroužen do ticha svého nitra.
The description He has given of realized souls
Jeho popis realizované duše
is so beautiful, if you could just experience it.
je tak nádherný, kdybyste to jen mohli zažít.
Namadeva, who was born much later, said that
Námadéva, který se narodil později, řekl,
you had that.
získali byste to nejvyšší.
I wish you all could read Amrutanubhava in English,
Přála bych si, abyste všichni mohli číst v angličtině Amrutanubhavu,
understanding how He describes a realized soul,
abyste pochopili, jak popisuje realizovanou duši,
and you'll find that within yourself it has happened.
zjistíte, že se to ve vašem nitru odehrálo.
You are different from others very much.
Tolik se lišíte od ostatních.
You'll be amazed how you have got such beautiful description of your Self.
Budete žasnout nad takovým nádherným popisem vašeho já.
I was talking about Maharashtrians; they are extremely talented people.
Mluvila jsem o lidech z Maháráštry, jsou to nesmírně talentovaní lidé.
See their music. In music no-one can beat them.
Například jejich hudba. V hudbě jsou úplně bezkonkurenční.
See their drama. In drama no-one can
Vezměte si jejich dramatickou tvorbu. Úplně bezkonkurenční.
You can see from films. In Maharashtra only
Vidíte to na jejich filmech, jen v Maháráštře
great films were created.
se natočily skvělé filmy.
The another one is Bengal, which is,
Další je Bengálsko, které je...
I would say, different but of the same level.
řekla bych, že jsou odlišní, ale na stejné úrovni.
It's such a talented people here,
Lidé tu jsou tak talentovaní,
it shows that God has a special blessing for these two,
že je vidět, že Bůh má pro tyto dvě země mimořádná požehnání,
and, should be, Maharashtrians should rise very high.
proto by lidé z Maháráštry měli stoupat opravdu vysoko.
But all the time complaining about others, talking ill of others,
Když si ale lidé budou pořád stěžovat na ostatní a mluvit o nich špatně,
and something very low they do. I'm surprised that,
je to velice nízká úroveň. Překvapilo Mě to,
I hope you don't pick up anything from them.
doufala jsem, že se to od nich nenaučíte.
And also the fussiness that is of the North Indians;
Také to, jak jsou lidé ze severní Indie hašteřiví,
that's also not a very good thing.
není moc dobrá věc.
It's surprising how you people have adjusted yourself to this country,
Je překvapivé, jak jste se vy této zemi přizpůsobili,
which has all kinds of parasites.
té zemi, která má tolik parazitů.
Because you live with vibrations, you feel the vibrations.
Protože žijete s vibracemi, cítíte vibrace.
It's something so great to see you all here,
Je skvělé vás tady všechny vidět,
and I'm telling them that they should try to understand you people.
říkám jim, že by se měli snažit vás pochopit.
Really I’m very proud of you all who have come all the way here.
Jsem velmi hrdá na všechny z vás, co jste přišli z takové dálky.
In this puja I am thinking of so many great saints who were born,
V této púdže myslím na mnoho skvělých světců, kteří se narodili,
who were great gurus, mahagurus. Of course Gyanesha,
kteří byli skvělými guruy, byli to maháguruové. Samozřejmě Gjanéša,
I must say, is the king of all those high, highly evolved souls, no doubt.
je králem všech těchto vysoce vyspělých duší, o tom není pochyb.
So we are now having a puja on the twenty -fourth of December
Takže nyní máme púdžu 24.prosince,
because it's a Datta Jayanti, Dattatreya's birth.
protože to je Datta Džajanti, narození Dattatréji.
And so we'll be having on the twenty-fourth night.
Budeme mít tedy púdžu dvacátého čtvrtého.
In any case it's a Christmas Eve. We could all start with that.
Je to samozřejmě Štědrý den. Tím bychom mohli začít.
And also Dattatreya, who took His form in Maharashtra.
Také Dattatréja, který se inkarnoval v Maháráštře.
Maharashtrians understand Dattatreya.
Lidé z Maháráštry Dattatréjovi rozumí,
They understand the Nath Panthis. These Nathas went all over.
rozumí Náth Panthiům. Tito Nathové se dostali všude.
They went to Kiev. You'll be amazed, they went even up to Bolivia,
Dostali se do Kyjeva, budete žasnout, ale i do Bolívie.
those who are from Maharashtra, from Rahuri. Can you imagine?
Lidé z Rahuri, z Maháráštry. Dovedete si to představit?
Such great people they were,
Takoví skvělí lidé tady byli
and that is what I expect to happen in this Maharashtra.
a to je to, co čekám, že se v Maháráštře stane.
And I'm sure one day I'll be very much happy with all of them; not few.
Jsem si jistá, že jednou budu s nimi všemi spokojená, ne jen s některými.
There are some very great Maharashtrians, no doubt,
V Maháráštře žijí i skvělí lidé, o tom nepochybuji,
but all of them have to join together because I talk of synthesis,
ale všichni se musí sjednotit, protože já mluvím o syntéze,
not of divisive method.
ne o rozdělení.
I hope they understand the inner feeling that I have,
Doufám, že rozumí tomu vnitřnímu pocitu, který mám,
otherwise all the good diamonds will be selected
protože všechny dobré diamanty budou vybrány,
and the ones which are defective will be thrown away.
ale kazové budou vyhozeny.
What's the use? But all of them are capable of achieving any height.
K čemu jsou kazové diamanty? Všichni jsou
but they are born in Maharashtra,
když se narodili v Maháráštře,
which is such a great country.
protože to je tak významná země.
So today they wanted to do Mahalakshmi,
Takže dnes chtěli dělat Mahálakšmí
this thing, we already have Mahalakshmi temple.
a tak dále - už máme chrám Mahálakšmí.
And they have a great blessing of Mahalakshmi also, in a way,
Požehnání od Mahálakšmí už svým způsobem mají,
but they lack: one is the wisdom,
ale chybí jim zaprvé moudrost
and the second the spirit of Kartikeya.
a zadruhé duch Kartikéji,
The spirit of Kartikeya - that
duch Kartikéji,
pure, absolute dynamism
chybí jim čistá, absolutní dynamika,
which doesn't indulge into nonsensical things and useless things;
která se neoddává nesmyslným, zbytečným věcem,
which shows results. May God bless you all!
dynamika, která má výsledky. Nechť vám Bůh všem žehná!